There isn't just one correct way to answer this question.
Bu sorunun tek bir doğru cevabı yok.
It really depends on what's most useful for you to identify the difference
Doğru uygulama davranışı ve yanlış uygulama davranışı arasındaki
between the incorrect app behavior and the correct app behavior.
farkı nasıl en kolay bir şekilde anlayacağınıza göre değişir.
In the incorrect app behavior, when you click on the order button
Yanlış davranışta sipariş tuşuna bastığımda,
the quantity changes to the same value each time and it shouldn't change.
miktar her seferinde aynı değer çıkıyor, ama bu olmamalı.
Next I also notice that the price was correct for
Aynı zamanda fiyatın bu miktar için doğru olduğunu,
this quantity value, but really the price should be for
ama adet seçicideki seçili son miktara göre
the last quantity that was selected in the quantity picker.
değişmesi gerektiğini de görüyorum.
Again, this is related to the fact that quantity shouldn't change.
Bu hata da miktarın aynı kalması gerekmesinden kaynaklanıyor.
Let's look at the existing code for why this is happening.
Bunun neden olduğunu anlamak için mevcut kodumuza bir bakalım.
In the activity_main layout file, We have the Order button declared here.
activity_main düzenleme dosyasında Order (Sipariş) butonumuz şurada.
When the Order button is clicked,
Order butonuna tıklayınca
we're going to call a method in the main activity called submitOrder.
MainActivity'den submitOrder adlı metodu çağırıyorum.
In the MainActivity.java file, here's the submitOrder method.
MainActivity.java dosyasında submitOrder metodu şurada.
This is old code from a long time ago that we haven't changed yet.
Bu henüz değiştirmediğimiz eski kodlardan biri.
But we create an integer quantity variable and initialize it to 5.
Biz de bir tam sayı miktar değişkeni belirliyor ve bunu ilk 5 seçiyoruz.
We display that to the screen.
Bunu ekranda görüntülüyoruz.
We also display price as the number of cups of coffee times $5 each.
Fiyatı da kahve sayısı çarpı 5$ olarak görüntülüyoruz.
Already this code don't make a lot of sense, because as we're trying to submit
Bu kod çok mantıklı gelmiyor, çünkü siparişi girerken
the order we're trying to update the quantity.
bir yandan miktarı güncellemeye çalışıyoruz.
And another problem is that we're creating an integer quantity variable
Diğer problem ise, bir tam sayı miktar değişkeni yaratıyoruz,
when we already have a global quantity variable that's supposed to keep track
oysa zaten kahve sayısını hesap etmek için kullandığımız
of the number of cups of coffee.
genel bir miktar değişkenimiz var.
so any method inside here can refer to this quantity variable.
dolayısıyla buradaki her metot bu miktar değişkenine işaret edebilir.
However, in the submitOrder method we're creating a new local quantity variable.
Ama submitOrder metodu içinde yeni bir yerel miktar değişkeni yaratıyoruz.
Technically you can have a local variable called the same name
Teknik olarak genel değişkenle aynı adı taşıyan bir yerel değişken
as a global variable.
olması mümkündür.
This just means that in the context of this method,
Bu sadece, bu metot özelinde
after this variable has been declared, whenever you refer to quantity,
bu değişken bildirildikten sonra miktardan bahsedilirken
it actually refers to this local quantity variable with value 5,
genel miktar değişkeni olan 2'ye değil, yerel miktar değişkeni olan
not the global quantity variable of value 2.
5 değerli değişkene işaret edildiği anlamına gelir.
This is the scope of this local variable.
Bu yerel değişkenin kapsamı budur.
Outside of this scope,
Bu kapsamın dışında
whenever you refer to quantity it means this global variable quantity.
ne zaman miktardan bahsedilse kastedilen genel miktar değişkenidir.
If you think about it,
Eğer düşünürseniz,
though, it doesn't really make sense that when you submit your order,
siparişinizi girdikten sonra yeni bir miktar yaratıp
you would create a new quantity and then display that on the screen.
ekranda onu görüntülemek çok mantıklı değil.
What you really want to do is just use the quantity that we've been keeping
İstediğimiz, kahve sayısını artırıp azaltırken
track of as we've been increasing and decreasing the number of cups of coffee.
takip ettiğimiz miktarı kullanmaya devam etmek.
So that's what we should calculate our price off of.
Fiyatımızı bu şekilde hesaplamalıyız.
To fix our code, we should not declare a local quantity variable.
Kodu düzeltmek içinse yerel bir miktar değişkeni bildirmemeli,
Instead we should just use this global quantity variable.
onun yerine genel miktar değişkenini kullanmaya devam etmeliyiz.
We should also stop trying to update the quantity on the screen.
Ekranımızdaki miktarı güncellemeye çalışmaktan da vazgeçmeliyiz.
The plus and minus buttons already handle updating the screen
Artı ve eksi butonları ekranı doğru miktar değerleriyle
with the proper quantity value.
zaten güncelliyor.
We do, however, want the submitOrder button to still update the price.
Fakat submitOrder butonuyla hâlen fiyatı güncellemek istiyoruz.
But this time we're going to calculate the price as quantity * 5
Ama bu sefer fiyatı miktar * 5 olarak hesaplayacağız
using the global quantity variable.
ve genel miktar değişkenini kullanacağız.
I'm going to update the code so that it reflects what we just talked about.
Kodu, konuştuklarımız uyarınca düzeltiyorum.
Notice that the quantity variable has turned into a purple font color,
Bakın miktar değişkeni nasıl mor renge dönüştü.
which means that we're using the global quantity variable in the MainActivity.
Bu MainActivity'deki genel miktar değişkenini kullandığımızı gösterir.
When the button is pressed it will trigger the submitOrder method.
Bu butona basılması submitOrder metodunu etkinleştirir.
This will display the price on the screen,
Bu, ekranda fiyatı gösterir.
where the price is calculated as the global quantity variable times 5.
Fiyat da genel miktar değişkeni çarpı 5 olarak hesaplanır.
This looks correct, so let's run it on our device.
Doğru gözüküyor, hadi cihazda deneyelim.
Okay, now for the ultimate test.
Şimdi de son test.
I'm going to change the quantity to 6 and then click on the Order button, and
Miktarı 6 yapıp Order butonuna basacağım.
Let me try other values as well so I know it's not a fluke.
Başka değerler de girelim de tesadüf olmadığına emin olalım.
That looks correct.
Doğru görünüyor. Bu da öyle.
You just fixed your first bug.
İlk hata düzeltmenizi yaptınız.
You did really well on that task.
Gerçekten çok iyiydiniz.
The functionality of our app is working really well.
Uygulamamızın işlevsellik kısmı çok iyi çalışıyor.
But I have to admit, the UI is a little bit ugly.
Ama itiraf etmeliyim ki kullanıcı arabirimi birazcık çirkin.
In particular, the quantity picker could use some UI love, so
Özellikle bu adet seçicinin biraz arabirim bakımına ihtiyacı var.
let's work on that next.
Şimdi de onu yapalım.